<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>PPRC Notes Home Page on</title><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/</link><description>Recent content in PPRC Notes Home Page on</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://yanfosec.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---anxiety-disorder-in-adolescents/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---anxiety-disorder-in-adolescents/</guid><description>Anxiety disorder is a mental health condition characterized by excessive and persistent worry, fear, and anxiety that interfere with daily activities 1. It&amp;rsquo;s the most common mental health disorder in the United States, affecting about 8% of children and teenagers 2.
Anxiety disorders in adolescents include specific phobias, social anxiety disorder, separation anxiety disorder, agoraphobia, panic disorder, and generalized anxiety disorder 1. Symptoms generally include excessive fears and worries, feelings of inner restlessness, and a tendency to be excessively wary and vigilant 3.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---anxiety-disorder/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---anxiety-disorder/</guid><description>Why is it a part of PRC? # Pain can cause Anxiety
Anxiety can cause pain symptoms
Anxiety can be a force for positive change&amp;hellip; # When it&amp;rsquo;s managed, it can be motivating Can be helpful Can protect
Anxiety is a problem when&amp;hellip; # Causes changes in behavior Interferes with social connections and engagement Anticipation of something bad happening that interferes with life Not proportional to the situation Symptoms of Anxiety # Physiology # Heart racing Nausea Sweating Excess Saliva Builtup Stomach discomfort Changes in appetite Changes in sleep Hyperventilating Tremors ## Psychology Can&amp;rsquo;t concentrate Mind Racing Worry Anger / Irritability Catastrphizing Cognitive Distortion ## Behaviors Avoidance Procrastination Nail biting/picking/hair pulling/bouncing leg Slamming doors Isolation Outburst Perfectionism [!</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---autonomic-dysfunction-pots/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---autonomic-dysfunction-pots/</guid><description>Overview from Copilot # Autonomic dysfunction, also known as autonomic neuropathy or dysautonomia, occurs when the nerves of the autonomic nervous system (ANS) are damaged. The ANS controls involuntary functions like heart rate, blood pressure, digestion, and temperature regulation 1. Here are some key points:
Symptoms:
Orthostatic hypotension: Dizziness upon standing. Exercise intolerance: Inability to alter heart rate during exercise. Sweating abnormalities: Alternating between excessive sweating and lack of sweating.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---bio-psycho-social-model/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---bio-psycho-social-model/</guid><description>Overview # Bio Psychological Social Hormone Change Stress Change in Friendships Puberty Sad Lack of Socialization COVID / Viral Illness Fear Peer Issues Injyry Anxieties Bullying Sensory Sensitivities Let Down by Doctors Parents Puillow Fluff &amp;amp; Others &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; Punish Sleep Avoidance School Trauma Procrastination Nutrition Transitions Medicines Cognitive Regidity &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; Flexibility Deconditioning Strong Willed Genetics Anger / Frustration Pain Behavior When rigidity starts to show # Remind to use skills Coach through the situation Remind to be a little flexible [!</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---biopsychosocial-factors/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---biopsychosocial-factors/</guid><description>Explore
refer to the interconnection between biology, psychology, and socio-environmental factors. These factors play a significant role in understanding health and wellness 1. Here&amp;rsquo;s a breakdown of each component:
Biological Factors: These include physiological factors such as genetics and illness pathology 1. Our physical well-being impacts our mental health for multiple reasons. For example, chronic pain can lead to symptoms of depression 1.
Psychological Factors: This involves thoughts, emotions, and behavior 1.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---cbt-as-treatment-for-anxiety-disorder/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---cbt-as-treatment-for-anxiety-disorder/</guid><description>Cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT) is a type of psychotherapy that&amp;rsquo;s often used to treat anxiety disorders 1 2. Here&amp;rsquo;s how it works:
Understanding Thought Patterns: CBT helps individuals identify and understand their negative thought patterns and behaviors that contribute to anxiety 1. Changing Thought Patterns: Once these negative thought patterns are identified, CBT works on changing them 1. This is done by challenging these thoughts and helping the individual replace them with more positive or realistic thoughts 1.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---central-sensitization/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---central-sensitization/</guid><description>Overview # Central sensitization is a condition of the nervous system that is associated with the development and maintenance of chronic pain 1. It is a pathophysiological process in which the central nervous system undergoes changes that alter its processing of pain and other sensory stimuli 2.
When central sensitization occurs, the nervous system goes through a process called wind-up and gets regulated in a persistent state of high reactivity 1.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---communication/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---communication/</guid><description>Communication # Verbal and non-verbal way of conveying thoughts
Why does it matter? # Help solve problems Improve soft skills Increase independence Prepare teens young adults for success in school, employment, and other settings Help families move away from symptom focused behaviors Help re-establish healthy reoles Assertive Communication using &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo; Statements # I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed I feel Because I want / prefer What you tyour thoughts [!idea] Most Important&amp;hellip; Most important part of communication is&amp;hellip; LISTENING</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---consequences-and-expectations/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---consequences-and-expectations/</guid><description>[PRC - Consequences](PRC - Consequences &amp;ldquo;wikilink&amp;rdquo;)
Consistent Attendance # From the moment kids wake up, they are assessing their symptoms, which needs to stop Kids need to get up knowing that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter how they are feeling Kids need to stay in school every day unless one of the below is true The high-risk period is 6 months to a year, which is especially important to focus on showing up for things no matter what Need to make staying home a lot less attractive &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; Need to establish rules for extreme situations when school may be missed ### 5 Reasons to miss school Fever (CDC Recommends 100.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---consequences-vs-punishment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---consequences-vs-punishment/</guid><description>The terms &amp;ldquo;consequences&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;punishments&amp;rdquo; are often used in the context of behavior management, and they have distinct meanings:
Consequences are the outcomes that result from one&amp;rsquo;s behavior 1. They can be natural (occurring naturally without any intervention) or logical (specifically planned by parents or other adults 1. Consequences are intended to teach individuals to take responsibility for their actions and learn from their mistakes 2. They respect the individual&amp;rsquo;s right to make a decision, even if it&amp;rsquo;s not a good one 1.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---consequences/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---consequences/</guid><description>Consequences Overview # It&amp;rsquo;s much more difficult to force consequences than rewards, especially with kids with chronic illnesses.
Overdoing rewards will not help in the long run.
Once you reward positives, that becomes the only reason. Once rewards are taken away, a person can fall back hard&amp;hellip;
Celebrating &amp;ldquo;first time&amp;rdquo; events are fine, but limited usefulness
Consequences are good for learning things quickly
Consequences should not be a surprise</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---depression/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---depression/</guid><description>Medications # Usually prescribed by experimentation Starts on a low-dose, and moves up from there
Evidenced Based intervention # Evidence-based interventions for depression are therapeutic practices or programs that have been proven effective through rigorous research and evaluation. These interventions are grounded in empirical evidence, clinical expertise, and patient characteristics.
In the context of depression treatment, evidence-based practice (EBP) aims to optimize the effectiveness of therapeutic interventions. It encourages therapists to use the best available research evidence to make informed decisions about patient care.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---diaphragmatic-breathing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---diaphragmatic-breathing/</guid><description>Why it works # Science! Activates the parasympathetic nervous system Changes balance of our blood chemistry Helps manage symptoms Breathing and the Nervous System # How does deep breathing help? The Sympathetic and Parasympathetic nervous system. - YouTube ### SUMMARY
Presenter discusses the benefits of deep breathing to activate the rest and digest response. ### IDEAS Deep breathing can help activate the parasympathetic nervous system for calmness and safety. Controlled deep breathing increases oxygen supply to the brain, aiding in stress response regulation.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---exposure-therapy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---exposure-therapy/</guid><description>Exposure Therapy # Exposure therapy is a type of cognitive-behavioral therapy that&amp;rsquo;s often used to treat anxiety disorders 1. It involves gradually and repeatedly exposing a person to the feared object, situation, or thought until the person becomes less anxious 1. Here&amp;rsquo;s how it works:
Understanding the Fear: The first step in exposure therapy is to understand the fear or anxiety trigger 1. This could be a specific object, situation, or thought 1.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---gratitude/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---gratitude/</guid><description>Gratitude: Research Supprted Benefits # Gratitude Improves Resilience # Linked to increased Optimism lifensatisfaction lower negative affect better experience in school Neuroscience # When practicing gratitude Neurochemicals associated with improved mood Stress hormones decrease Neurons that fire together wire together
Five depths of gratitude video # Five Depths of Gratitude - YouTube
Ungrateful: At this level, people don&amp;rsquo;t know how to be grateful. They feel supremely entitled and harbor callous disregard for others&amp;rsquo; preferences¹.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---growth-mindset-and-chronic-pain-recovery/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---growth-mindset-and-chronic-pain-recovery/</guid><description>Growth Mindset and Chronic Pain Recovery # Fixed mindset is all about accepting limitations Growth mindset is all about the confidence in evolving and growing with effort ## Definitions
The difference between a growth mindset and a fixed mindset in the context of child development and parenting.
Fixed Mindset: This mindset is based on the belief that a person&amp;rsquo;s abilities, intelligence, and talents are fixed traits that cannot be significantly changed or developed.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---morning-session/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---morning-session/</guid><description>[PRC - Bringing PRC Home](PRC - Bringing PRC Home &amp;ldquo;wikilink&amp;rdquo;)
Other Considerations # No sleep-overs for 6 months, need to stick to the schedule</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---neuroplasticity-video/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---neuroplasticity-video/</guid><description>YouTube # SUMMARY The transcript discusses neuroplasticity, the brain&amp;rsquo;s ability to change throughout life, forming new pathways by rewiring.
IDEAS # Brain changes throughout life. Neuroplasticity allows for forming new pathways. Habits strengthen pathways in the brain. Rewiring the brain involves forming new connections and weakening old ones. Learning new tasks carves out new pathways in the brain. Changing thoughts or emotions creates new neural pathways. Directed attention can help rewire the brain.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---pain-behaviors-and-warm-neutrality/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---pain-behaviors-and-warm-neutrality/</guid><description>What is Pain Behavior? # [!NOTE] Definition Any thoughts, verbalization &amp;amp; non-verbal behaviors that communicate that something is wrong
Central sensitization is a pathophysiological process in which the central nervous system undergoes changes that alter its processing of pain and other sensory stimuli 1. This process can make the nervous system more sensitive to stimuli, leading to an increased response to pain 2.
Pain behavior, in this context, refers to the set of verbal and nonverbal expressions that accompany the experience of pain.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---parent-group-contacts/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---parent-group-contacts/</guid><description>Andrea - acde09@gmail.com Trish - Trishk555@gmail.com Lynette - Lynettedolan@hotmail.com Dave - dave.dachs@gmail.com Clay - William.clay.cochran@gmail.com</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---plans-for-going-home/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---plans-for-going-home/</guid><description>Rules # Need to figure out which strategies apply to who in the house? Chores should apply to all kids Rules like napping should apply to all Adults napping is OK, as long as it&amp;rsquo;s kept away from the kids and no bragging Figure out what to share and who to share it with, so limit or minimize questions about health. Steve &amp;amp; Ksusha? Igor and Natasha? [!NOTE] With well-wishers Don&amp;rsquo;t talk about symptoms</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---prescribing-cascade/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---prescribing-cascade/</guid><description>A prescribing cascade is a sequence of events where an adverse drug event is misinterpreted as a new medical condition, leading to the prescription of an additional, potentially avoidable, medication 1 2. This process can lead to further side effects and unanticipated drug interactions, which may result in further symptoms and misdiagnoses 3.
For example, a patient might be prescribed a calcium channel blocker, which can cause ankle edema. If this side effect is misinterpreted as a new medical condition, a diuretic might be prescribed to treat the edema 2.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---relapse-prevention/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---relapse-prevention/</guid><description>PRC is NOT # Not about doing something once
PRC IS # Continuing to do things even when not 100%
Key Concepts # New Mindset
Asking the question: What can I do to manage this?
Especially useful for new symptoms
Difficult Day vs Lapse vs Relapse # Difficult Day - High symptoms/stress but still using PRC concepts Lapse - brief return to old habits in a moment of symptoms/stress, return to habits in one behavior Relapse - prolonged return to old habits in many behaviors, decreased functioning, may need more intense intervention [!</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---sleep-and-chronic-symptoms/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---sleep-and-chronic-symptoms/</guid><description>Sleep Importance # Physical, emotional, and mental health 1/3 of our lives sleeping Most have trouble sleeping at some point. Sleep problems are common with chronic pain Sleep and Chronic Pain # Poor sleep will cause an increase in pain Disrupted sleep can cause pain to increase Circadian Rhythms # Circadian Rhythms are 24-hour cycles that are part of the body&amp;rsquo;s internal clock, running in the background to carry out essential functions and processes 1.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---understanding-pain-in-5-minutes-video/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---understanding-pain-in-5-minutes-video/</guid><description>YouTube # SUMMARY: The transcript discusses chronic pain, emphasizing that it is produced by the brain and can be managed through a holistic approach.
IDEAS: # Pain, whether acute or chronic, is always produced by the brain, not necessarily due to tissue damage. Chronic pain affects one in five people in Australia, with the brain continuing to produce pain. Retraining the brain and nervous system is crucial in managing persistent pain effectively.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---video-on-effects-of-talking-about-pain/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---video-on-effects-of-talking-about-pain/</guid><description>YouTube # ONE SENTENCE SUMMARY: Stanford University researcher Sean Mackey found a way for people to use their brain to control pain.
MAIN POINTS: # Debra considers decorations indoors due to back pain limiting outdoor activities. Sean Mackey&amp;rsquo;s experiment taught people to control their brain&amp;rsquo;s pain perception. The experiment focused on the cingulate cortex, a part of the brain perceiving pain. MRI scanner allowed real-time observation of brain activity related to pain perception.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---why-things-hurt-video/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/source/prc---why-things-hurt-video/</guid><description>TEDxAdelaide - Lorimer Moseley - Why Things Hurt - YouTube
SUMMARY # Dr. Lorimer Moseley explains the neurobiology of pain, illustrating how the brain processes pain signals and how pain is a construct of the brain.
IDEAS # Pain is an illusion constructed by the brain to protect the body from perceived danger. Visual illusions demonstrate how the brain interprets and creates perceptions, including pain. The brain evaluates sensory input to determine the level of danger and whether pain is necessary.</description></item><item><title>Acceptance and Commitment Therapy</title><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/acceptance-and-commitment-therapy-act/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/acceptance-and-commitment-therapy-act/</guid><description>PPRC Home
CBT Triangle # ![[images/cbt-triangle-black.png]]
ACT Hexaflex Copilot # ACT stands for Acceptance and Commitment Therapy, which is a third-wave Cognitive-Behavioral Therapy (CBT) that incorporates mindfulness 1. The Hexaflex model is a hexagonally shaped visual aid used in ACT to classify and treat client problems holistically 1. It consists of six core processes that correspond to the core ACT principles 1:
Present Moment: ACT is a present-moment-focused therapy. The purpose of this focus on the present moment is to restore a sense of control lost in many clients seeking therapy or coaching 1.</description></item><item><title>Acceptance and Commitment Therapy (ACT)</title><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/concepts/acceptance-and-commitment-therapy-act/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/concepts/acceptance-and-commitment-therapy-act/</guid><description>PPRC Home
CBT Triangle # ![[images/cbt-triangle-black.png]]
ACT Hexaflex Copilot # ACT stands for Acceptance and Commitment Therapy, which is a third-wave Cognitive-Behavioral Therapy (CBT) that incorporates mindfulness 1. The Hexaflex model is a hexagonally shaped visual aid used in ACT to classify and treat client problems holistically 1. It consists of six core processes that correspond to the core ACT principles 1:
Present Moment: ACT is a present-moment-focused therapy. The purpose of this focus on the present moment is to restore a sense of control lost in many clients seeking therapy or coaching 1.</description></item><item><title>Acute and Chronic Pain and Symptoms</title><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/concepts/acute-and-chronic-pain-and-symptoms/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/concepts/acute-and-chronic-pain-and-symptoms/</guid><description>Difference between Acute and Chronic Symptoms # How the human body perceives pain # The human body perceives pain through a complex process involving the nervous system. Here&amp;rsquo;s a simplified explanation:
Pain Detection: Our body is covered with pain receptors, also known as sensory cells. These cells are found in our muscles, internal organs, and skin 1. When a part of your body is injured, these special pain receptors release chemicals called neurotransmitters 2.</description></item><item><title>Acute and Chronic Pain and Symptoms</title><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/concepts/prc---acute-and-chronic-pain-and-symptoms/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/concepts/prc---acute-and-chronic-pain-and-symptoms/</guid><description>Difference between Acute and Chronic Symptoms # How the human body perceives pain # The human body perceives pain through a complex process involving the nervous system. Here&amp;rsquo;s a simplified explanation:
Pain Detection: Our body is covered with pain receptors, also known as sensory cells. These cells are found in our muscles, internal organs, and skin 1. When a part of your body is injured, these special pain receptors release chemicals called neurotransmitters 2.</description></item><item><title>Mayo's PPRC Program Overview</title><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/pprc-home/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/pprc-home/</guid><description>![[images/prc_overview.png]]
Concepts to Understand Concepts to Understand # Code of Conduct Code of Conduct # Long-Term Success Long-Term Success # Acute and Chronic Pain and Symptoms
Notes # Acceptance and Commitment Therapy (ACT)
[PRC - Consequences](PRC - Consequences &amp;ldquo;wikilink&amp;rdquo;) [PRC - Plans for going home](PRC - Plans for going home &amp;ldquo;wikilink&amp;rdquo;) [Central Sensitization](Central Sensitization &amp;ldquo;wikilink&amp;rdquo;) [PRC - Consequences and Expectations](PRC - Consequences and Expectations &amp;ldquo;wikilink&amp;rdquo;) [PRC - Growth Mindset and Chronic Pain Recovery](PRC - Growth Mindset and Chronic Pain Recovery &amp;ldquo;wikilink&amp;rdquo;)</description></item></channel></rss>