<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title/><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/concepts/</link><description>Recent content on</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://yanfosec.github.io/concepts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Acceptance and Commitment Therapy (ACT)</title><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/concepts/acceptance-and-commitment-therapy-act/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/concepts/acceptance-and-commitment-therapy-act/</guid><description>PPRC Home
CBT Triangle # ![[images/cbt-triangle-black.png]]
ACT Hexaflex Copilot # ACT stands for Acceptance and Commitment Therapy, which is a third-wave Cognitive-Behavioral Therapy (CBT) that incorporates mindfulness 1. The Hexaflex model is a hexagonally shaped visual aid used in ACT to classify and treat client problems holistically 1. It consists of six core processes that correspond to the core ACT principles 1:
Present Moment: ACT is a present-moment-focused therapy. The purpose of this focus on the present moment is to restore a sense of control lost in many clients seeking therapy or coaching 1.</description></item><item><title>Acute and Chronic Pain and Symptoms</title><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/concepts/acute-and-chronic-pain-and-symptoms/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/concepts/acute-and-chronic-pain-and-symptoms/</guid><description>Difference between Acute and Chronic Symptoms # How the human body perceives pain # The human body perceives pain through a complex process involving the nervous system. Here&amp;rsquo;s a simplified explanation:
Pain Detection: Our body is covered with pain receptors, also known as sensory cells. These cells are found in our muscles, internal organs, and skin 1. When a part of your body is injured, these special pain receptors release chemicals called neurotransmitters 2.</description></item><item><title>Biopsychosocial Factors</title><link>https://yanfosec.github.io/concepts/biopsychosocial-factors/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yanfosec.github.io/concepts/biopsychosocial-factors/</guid><description>This concept refers to the interconnection between biology, psychology, and socio-environmental factors. These factors play a significant role in understanding health and wellness 1. Here&amp;rsquo;s a breakdown of each component:
Biological Factors: These include physiological factors such as genetics and illness pathology 1. Our physical well-being impacts our mental health for multiple reasons. For example, chronic pain can lead to symptoms of depression 1.
Psychological Factors: This involves thoughts, emotions, and behavior 1.</description></item></channel></rss>